A Finding Aid to the Douglas Leigh Papers, 1903-1999, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Douglas Leigh Papers
1903-1999
Archives of American Art
Leigh, Douglas
AAA.leigdoug
Archival Resource Key
17.6 Linear feet
The collection measures 17.6 linear feet and dates from 1903 to 1999 (bulk 1924-1992) and documents the career of advertising designer and executive Douglas Leigh. Found are 83 volumes of publicity scrapbooks that contain mostly photographs, clippings, printed materials, and scattered letters, drawings, and blueprints. Also included are professional correspondence; photographs of project installations, aerial advertising, and entertainers; plaques and awards received by Leigh; and printed material, which includes clippings, press kits, advertising materials, designs and original sketches for projects by Leigh. The material reflects Leigh's continuously imaginative use of a wide range of media in promoting his clients' products. Among the projects/campaigns represented are 7up, Airships (Tydol, Flying Red Horse, MGM, Wonder Bread and others), Allied Chemical Tower, Amoco, BlueCross-Blue Shield, Camel cigarettes, Coca-Cola, EPOK, Eveready, Flamingo Frozen Foods, Four Roses Whiskey, Fram Oil Filters, Helmsley Building, Old Gold Cigarettes, Pan Am Building, Pepsi-Cola, R. J. Reynolds, Schaefer Beer, Spectaculars, Stag Beer, Times Tower Building, and Wilson Whiskey.
Biographical Note
Douglas Leigh was born in Anniston, Alabama, in 1907. After graduating from the University of Florida in 1928, he began his career as a salesman for the General Outdoor Advertising Company of Atlanta, Georgia. He moved to New York City in 1930 and developed his ideas for animated and illuminated advertising signs primarily in the vicinity of Times Square. He established his own advertising company, Douglas Leigh, Inc., in 1933 and created the popular Camel Cigarette billboard that featured a man's face exhaling smoke rings over Broadway.
Dubbed "The Man Who Lit Up New York" in his New York Times obituary, he was responsible for festooning Broadway with miles of spectacular electrical and animated signs, such as a steaming coffeepot, a winking penguin on a cake of ice for Kool cigarettes, and the giant Camel sign that puffed smoke rings from a Times Square sign from 1941 and 1967. These effects led to creating animated billboards, an innovation called the Leigh-EPOK animated, billboards matrix display, or EPOK. Leigh developed numerous dirigible advertising projects involving both painted logos and networks of lights over the surface of the dirigible. These sequentially-timed lights caused dramatic animated effects against the night sky.
Leigh was also a pioneer in the illumination of city skylines and buildings and thought of lighting up Manhattan's skyscrapers, beginning with the Empire State Building, in 1976 and continuing with the lighting and gilding of the Con Edison Building, the Helmsley Building, and the Crown Building. This idea was adopted by many other cities, including Cincinnati, Atlanta, Orlando, Miami, New Orleans, and Baltimore with Leigh traveling there to supervise the final installation. Leigh was also involved with numerous urban improvement and renewal projects.
Leigh's career continued into the 1990's, and he died in 1999.
Scope and Content Note
The collection measures 17.6 linear feet and dates from 1903 to 1999 (bulk 1924-1992) and documents the career of advertising designer and executive Douglas Leigh. Found are 83 volumes of publicity scrapbooks that contain mostly photographs, clippings, printed materials, and scattered letters, drawings, and blueprints. Also included are professional correspondence; photographs of project installations, aerial advertising, and entertainers; plaques and awards received by Leigh; and printed material, which includes clippings, press kits, advertising materials, designs and original sketches for projects by Leigh. The material reflects Leigh's continuously imaginative use of a wide range of innovative media in promoting his clients' products.
Among the projects and campaigns represented in the papers are 7up, Airships (Tydol, Flying Red Horse, MGM, Wonder Bread and others), Allied Chemical Tower, Amoco, BlueCross-Blue Shield, Camel cigarettes, Coca-Cola, EPOK, Eveready, Flamingo Frozen Foods, Four Roses Whiskey, Fram Oil Filters, Helmsley Building, Old Gold Cigarettes, Pan Am Building, Pepsi-Cola, R. J. Reynolds, Schaefer Beer, Spectaculars, Stag Beer, Times Tower Building, and Wilson Whiskey.
The Personal Scrapbooks Series (.06 linear feet) consists of 4 scrapbooks that contain photographs, letters, and printed material that document Douglas Leigh's interaction with family, friends, and colleagues.
The General Scrapbooks Series (4.0 linear feet) consists of 16 scrapbooks containing clippings, miscellaneous printed material, letters, interview transcripts, artwork, photographs, and a metal Tydol pin that document the development of miscellaneous projects by Douglas Leigh and his company.
The Billboard Project Files Series (5.0 linear feet) consists primarily of scrapbooks, photographs, and individual product files that document the development of billboard advertising projects.
The Poster Project Files Series (1.6 linear feet) consists of notes, reports, artwork, photographs, miscellaneous printed material, 4 scrapbooks, and individual product files that document the development of poster advertising projects, primarily those used on Railway Express Agency delivery trucks.
The Dirigible Project Files Series (3.7 linear feet) consists of notes, reports, artwork, photographs, miscellaneous printed material, 12 scrapbooks, and individual product files that document the development of dirigible advertising projects involving both painted logos and networks of lights over the surface of the dirigible. These sequentially-timed lights caused dramatic animated effects against the night sky.
The Urban Improvement Project Files Series (2.2 linear feet) consists of photographs, a promotion book, clippings, miscellaneous printed material, 18 scrapbooks, and individual urban improvement project files that document the development of urban improvement projects involving both the construction design of new buildings and the lighting of prominent buildings in New York City and elsewhere.
Arrangement
Scrapbooks within Series 8-13 (Personal Scrapbooks, General Scrapbooks, Billboard Project Files, Poster Project Files, Dirigible Project Files, and Urban Improvement Project Files) have been arranged into as accurate a chronological order as possible. They have been numbered consecutively within each series, and scrapbooks containing material concerning multiple products appear before those concerning individual products.
Oversized materials from various series have been housed in Boxes 6-11, Boxes 12-32 (sols), BV 33, and OV 34, and are noted in the Series Description/Container Listing Section at the appropriate folder title with see also/see references. Additional oversized boxes may be listed with the appropriate series when they contain oversized material from one series only.
The collection has been arranged into 13 series:
Missing Title
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1943-1988 (Box 1, 12; 6 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1924-1999, n.d. (Box 1; 16 folders)
Series 3: Notes, 1941-1997, n.d. (Box 1; 3 folders)
Series 4: Writings by Others, 1962, n.d. (Box 1; 2 folders)
Series 5: Artwork, 1958 (Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 6: Photographs, 1913-1990 (Box 1, 12; .03 linear feet)
Series 7: Printed Material, 1905-1999, n.d. (Box 1; 22 folders)
Series 8: Personal Scrapbooks, 1942-1982 (Box 12-13; .06 linear feet)
Series 9: General Scrapbooks, 1933-1951 (Box 2-5; 4.0 linear feet)
Series 10: Billboard Project Files, 1929-1997 (Box 1, 6-7, 14-25, BV 33; 5.0 linear feet)
Series 11: Poster Project Files, 1943-1963 (Box 7-8, 14; 1.6 linear feet)
Series 12: Dirigible Project Files, 1944-1954 (Box 8-11, 14, 26-28; 3.7 linear feet)
Series 13: Urban Improvement Project Files, 1903-1992 (Box 9, 14, 28-32, OV 34; 2.2 linear feet)
Provenance
The Douglas Leigh papers were donated to the Archives of American Art by Leigh's widow, Elsie M. Leigh, in 2000.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Patrons must use microfilm copy. Original scrapbooks are closed to researchers because of their fragile condition.
Alternative Forms Available
The collection is available on 35 mm microfilm reels 5840-5848 at the Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of the material described in the container inventory does not reflect the arrangement of the collection on microfilm.
Signs and signboards; Interviews; Transcripts; advertising; Light in architecture; Designers -- New York (State) -- New York; Sketches; Scrapbooks; Blueprints; Seven-Up Company; R.J. Reynolds Industries; Eveready Battery Company; Pepsi-Cola Company; Coca-Cola Company; Amoco Oil Company.
- Biographical Material, 1943-1988; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; (Box 1, 12; 6 folders)
  Scope and Contents note
  Military records document Leigh's service in the U.S. Navy during World War II. Biographical material includes certificates of membership in naval and real estate organizations, and award plaques and certificates. Records are arranged chronologically.
  Existence and Location of Copies
  Biographical materials are on reel 5840.
  - Military Service Records, 1943-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Membership Certificates (see also Box 12), 1945-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Award Certificates and Plaques (see also Box 12), 1958-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bank of New York Medal, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Greenville High School Hall of Fame Plaque, 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Oversize Membership and Award Certificates, 1945, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1924-1999, n.d.; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; (Box 1; 16 folders)
  The chronologically-arranged correspondence consists of business letters that do not directly relate to a specific project.
  Correspondence is on reel 5840.
  - Correspondence, Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1947-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1950-1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1954-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1963-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1973-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1987-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1990-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1994-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Notes, 1941-1997, n.d.; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; (Box 1; 3 folders)
  Notes consist of address lists of business associates, a haphazard collection of clippings entitled "Recognition of Results Obtained," and miscellaneous notes.
  Notes are on reel 5840.
  - Address Lists, n.d.; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - "Recognition of Results Obtained,", 1941-1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, 1994-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Writings by Others, 1962, n.d.; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; (Box 1; 2 folders)
  This series consists of miscellaneous poems and a typescript of remarks by James Felt to the Broadway Association.
  Writings by others are on reel 5840.
  - Miscellaneous Poems, n.d.; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Typescript of Remarks by James Felt, 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Artwork, 1958; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; (Box 1; 1 folder)
  Artwork consists of three caricatures of Douglas Leigh by Faruk Alpkurt.
  Artwork is on reel 5840.
  - Caricatures of Leigh by Faruk Alpkurt, 1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Photographs, 1913-1990; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; (Box 1, 12; .03 linear feet)
  Photographs are of Douglas Leigh, his boyhood home, family members, and business colleagues. Photographs of Leigh and business colleagues ca. 1939 include a photo of Mickey Rooney. An album contains photographs of office parties at Douglas Leigh, Inc.
  Photographs are on reel 5840.
  - Photographs of Leigh, His Brother, and Boyhood Home, 1913-1920; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Photographs of Douglas Leigh (see Box 12), ca. 1928-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29-35)
  - Photographs of Leigh's Business Colleagues, 1926; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Photographs of Leigh and Business Colleagues, ca. 1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Photographs of Leigh and Business Colleagues, ca. 1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 38-39)
  - Photographs of Leigh and Business Colleagues, 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Photograph Album of Douglas Leigh, Inc., Office Parties (see also Box 12), 1941-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Oversize Photograph of Leigh and a Colleague, ca. 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Photograph Album of Douglas Leigh, Inc., Office Parties, 1941-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Printed Material, 1905-1999, n.d.; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; (Box 1; 22 folders)
  Printed material including clippings, brochures, picture postcards, 2 books, a sample book of business stationery, and miscellaneous printed material.
  Printed materials are on reels 5840-5841.
  - Clippings, 1905-1999, n.d.; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 42-56)
  - Brochure, "Point of Most Return,", n.d.; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Brochure, "Urban Light Tours Manhattan,", 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Picture Postcards, n.d.; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Color Planning for Business and Industry by Howard Ketcham, 1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - The Most Colorful Book Ever!, 1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Sample Book of Business Stationery, ca. 1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1925, n.d.; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 63)
- Personal Scrapbooks, 1942-1982; Series 8; Archival Resource Key; (Box 12-13; .06 linear feet)
  These personal scrapbooks contain photographs, letters, and printed material documenting Douglas Leigh's interaction with family, friends, and colleagues. One scrapbook contains photographs of Leigh's parents and a skiing holiday. The other scrapbooks record annual business luncheons of the New York Sales Executive Club and the Broadway Association. Personal Scrapbook 3 contains 2 letters and a photograph of John D. Rockefeller III.
  Personal scrapbooks are on reel 5841.
  - Personal Scrapbook 1, 1942-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Personal Scrapbook 2, 25th Annual Luncheon, 1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Personal Scrapbook 3, Broadway Association 51st Annual Luncheon, 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Personal Scrapbook 4, Broadway Association 71st Annual Luncheon, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 3)
- General Scrapbooks, 1933-1951; Series 9; Archival Resource Key; (Box 2-5; 4.0 linear feet)
  The sixteen general scrapbooks found here contain clippings, miscellaneous printed material, letters, interview transcripts, artwork, and photographs documenting the development of miscellaneous projects by Douglas Leigh and his company. General Scrapbook 1 contains a cartoon of Douglas Leigh by Stookie Allen. General Scrapbook 13 contains a metal pin reading "Honorary Tydol Pilot/ Feb 1947."
  General scrapbooks are on reels 5841-5843.
  - General Scrapbook 1, 1933-1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - General Scrapbook 2, 1937-1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - General Scrapbook 3, 1937-1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - General Scrapbook 4, 1938-1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - General Scrapbook 5, 1941-1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - General Scrapbook 6, 1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - General Scrapbook 7, 1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - General Scrapbook 8, 1944-1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - General Scrapbook 9, 1943-1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - General Scrapbook 10, 1945-1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - General Scrapbook 11, 1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - General Scrapbook 12, 1947-1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - General Scrapbook 13, 1944-1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - General Scrapbook 14, 1947-1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - General Scrapbook 15, 1948-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - General Scrapbook 16, 1948-1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Billboard Project Files, 1929-1997; Series 10; Archival Resource Key; (Box 1, 6, 14-25, BV 33; 5.0 linear feet)
  This series consists primarily of 29 scrapbooks and photographs documenting the development of billboard advertising projects, including Leigh's inventions of the Leigh-EPOK Electric Display Board and the Tri-Vision Billboard. Also found are notes, letters, interview transcripts, clippings, miscellaneous printed material, and individual product files. Scrapbooks have been consecutively numbered within this series. Scrapbooks containing material concerning multiple products appear before those concerning individual products. Leigh referred to his billboards as "Spectaculars" because they often were illuminated or displayed mechanized animation.
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged chronologically within each project, with the exception of 10.2: General Photographs, which has been arranged according to subject matter, and 10.5: Individual Billboard Product Files, which has been arranged alphabetically. The series is divided into 5 subseries:
  10.1: General Notes, 1934-1997
  10.2: General Photographs, 1929-1996
  10.3: Leigh-EPOK Electric Display Board, 1966-1993
  10.4: Billboard Scrapbooks for Miscellaneous Products, 1933-1977
  10.5: Individual Billboard Product Files, 1936-1980
  Billboard project files are on reels 5843-5845.
  - General Notes, 1934-1997; 10.1; Archival Resource Key
    - Chronologies of Spectaculars, 1993-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Miscellaneous Ideas for Spectaculars, n.d.; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Miscellaneous Ideas for Spectaculars, 1934; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Miscellaneous Ideas for Spectaculars, 1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Miscellaneous Ideas for Spectaculars, 1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - Miscellaneous Ideas for Spectaculars, 1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous Ideas for Spectaculars, 1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous Ideas for Spectaculars (see Box 14), 1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous Ideas for Spectaculars, 1949-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous Ideas for Spectaculars (see Box 14), 1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous Ideas for Spectaculars, 1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous Ideas for Spectaculars, 1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous Ideas for Spectaculars, 1954-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Statistics and Photos Concerning Sign Locations, 1945-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Map of Columbus Circle Area (see Box 14), 1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Oversized Drawings of Ideas for Spectaculars and Map of Columbus Circle, 1946-1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - General Photographs, 1929-1996; 10.2; Archival Resource Key
    - Ideas for Spectaculars, 1945-1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 11-12)
    - Buildings in Atlanta, Georgia, 1996, n.d.; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Boardwalk, Atlantic City, New Jersey, 1937; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Buildings in Chicago, Illinois, 1958-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - 112 Madison Avenue, Detroit, Michigan, 1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Buildings in Los Angeles, California, 1948-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 17-18)
    - New York City Skyline (see Box 14), 1959, n.d.; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Times Square, New York City (see also Box 14), 1929-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 20-31)
    - Columbus Circle, New York City (see also Box 14), 1934-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 32-39)
    - Sixth Avenue and Radio City, New York City, 1942-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 40)
    - Bryant Park, New York City, 1929-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 41)
    - Wurlitzer Building (120 W 42nd), New York City, 1950-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 42)
    - 522 Fifth Avenue, New York City, 1955-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 43)
    - 40 Wall Street, New York City, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 44)
    - Statue of Liberty, New York City, 1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 45)
    - Miscellaneous Buildings, New York City, 1940-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 46)
    - Miscellaneous buildings, Brooklyn, New York, 1940-1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - Miscellaneous Buildings, Queens and The Bronx, 1940-1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 48)
    - Oakland, California Skyline, Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - Unidentified U. S. cities, n.d.; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - Miscellaneous Foreign Cities (see also Box 14, 1966, n.d.; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 51-52)
    - Tri-Vision Billboard Photographs of Fabrication, ca. 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - Oversized Photographs of New York City, 1945-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Canada Dry Sign
      Chevrolet Sign
      Planters Peanuts Sign
      2 Views of Times Square
      Coca-Cola Sign
      Columbus Circle
    - Oversized Photograph of a Building in Moscow, Russia, n.d.; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Leigh-EPOK Electric Display Board, 1966-1993; 10.3; Archival Resource Key
    - Leigh-EPOK Notebook with 5 Photos, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - Animation Inventory Lists, 1991-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 55)
    - Photographs of Signs and Performers, ca. 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 56)
    - Brochures About the Leigh-EPOK Sign, ca. 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 57)
    - Booklet About the Leigh-EPOK Sign, ca. 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 58)
  - Billboard Scrapbooks for Miscellaneous Products, 1933-1977; 10.4; Archival Resource Key